A Guide to the The Papers of Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1813-1904, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Letters by and Related to Nathaniel Hawthorne
  - Subseries A: Dated Letters
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to Julia E. Gibson, 1860 March 29, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:63)
      Acknowledging her request for his autograph. #6249-d.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 April 26, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:64)
      Hoping warmer weather will strengthen Mrs. Hawthorne and that Bennoch will visit. Is himself soon visiting [John Lothrop] Motley, who invited him to London, but, where he prefers staying no more than a week, and with an invitation could go on to visit Bennoch. Also requesting a message be sent on to Fields. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 May 22, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:65)
      Outlining plans for a trip to Cambridge, rather than the Derby, despite hearing he shouldn't miss the latter, and possibly on to see Bennoch. #6249-a.
    - N[athaniel] H[awthorne] to "My dear old Boy" (his son Julian), 1860 May 22, ALS, 4 pp., on 1 sheet folded and tipped to a blank leaf also bearing 2 clipped autographs ("Hawthorne." and "Una Hawthorne/1854"). (Box-folder 2:66)
      Praising his son's recent good behavior at home, then exclaiming about Americans' prowess against English contenders, both in boxing with American [John] Heenan vs. [Tom] Sayers, and in horse racing with the good American Derby entrant to run at Epsom. Summarizing his current travel schedule for London, Cambridge, and Canterbury, which will delay their eventual departure together for Liverpool. #6249-a
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to W[illiam] C[ox] Bennett, 1860 June 15, ALS, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:67)
      On the eve of departing for America, thanking Bennett for "the beautiful sonnets with which you have honored me and my book" and that this note is the "very last use that I make of my pen in England." #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "My dear Sir" [Dr. John Brown], 1860 June 15, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 2:68)
      Praises and thanks the Scottish author John Brown for his fine story Rab and his Friends. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to L.A. Surette, 1860 October 10, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., laid down on a blank leaf. (Box-folder 2:69)
      Declines the Concord Lyceum curator's invitation to speak, despite his sense of duty as a "townsman," but doesn't speak before the public. #6249-a.
    - S[ophia] Hawthorne to Mr. & Mrs. Waterston, 1860 December 2, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. folded. (Box-folder 2:70)
      Expresses grief and sympathy to her friends on the loss of their only daughter, Helen, her feelings deepened by having nursed Una through serious illness [malaria], but also reassurance through faith in God's wisdom and consolation. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Chas. H. Bowen, 1860 December 5, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., affixed to a blank leaf, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:71)
      Responds to a request for his signature. #6249-a.
    - N[athanie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1860 December 17, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 2:72)
      Comments on missing Bennoch since returning from England, on settling slowly into the Wayside where a room has been designated "Bennoch's Room" for his visits and another where N.H. plans to write his next novel, on how the family members are, and on the future of his country now at war. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to F.R. Shelton, 1862 August 28, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., inlaid in a larger leaf, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:1)
      Complying with Shelton's request, for an autograph. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Francis] Bennoch, 1862 October 12, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 2 pp. (Box-folder 3:2)
      Acknowledges that the American Civil War, an inevitability about whose outcome he is pessimistic, pervades his thoughts and outlook for the future; welcomes news of Bennoch's "returning prosperity," a blessing for him and the many beneficiaries of his generous nature, and assesses his own circumstances as fully sufficient, given God's tendency to balance good fortune with bad; believes a product of the war experience will be better writers than those of his own generation; considers his own literary reputation to be negligible; sends a recent photograph of himself and sees in the Bennochs' likenesses little change. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to William. D. Ticknor, 1862 October 21, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:3)
      Owing George P. Bradford money, N.H. asks that Ticknor pay the debt on his behalf. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1862 November 30, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. folded, with autograph envelope and with a later leaf of quotations in manuscript concerning S.H.'s regard for Hitchcock. (Box-folder 3:4)
      Some three months after seeing him last, S.H. reaffirms her vast admiration for him and his superlative religious insight, describes the unique rapport she feels with him, acknowledges receiving his books on Christianity and alchemy, expands upon their benefits for her spirituality. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1862 December 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:5)
      Having learned of his being in Washington, she begs him to retrieve her recent letter, sent to his New York address, so as to keep it from exposure to anyone but himself. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to William A. Wheeler, 1862 December 31, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:6)
      Confirms his enthusiasm for Wheeler's dictionary [of fictional characters] project, noting a similar idea he had once entertained, encourages him to include name pronunciations, advises him about British copyright considerations, and agrees to review "specimens." #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Roberts Brothers, 1863 January 7, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p., 2 copies. (Box-folder 3:7)
      Thanks them for sending a copy of Jean Ingelow's poems, praising both the poems and the publishers for putting her work before the public. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Prof. [Ephraim Whitman] Gurney, 1863 March 13, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:8)
      Forwards a letter assessing Julian's work. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1863 August 9, ALS, 16 pp. on 4 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:9)
      A long monologue, in lieu of the personal conversation with General Hitchcock that she would prefer to have, reaffirming her faith in and admiration for him as philosopher, author, and source of ideas that, together with God's laws and if fully applied, would avert much of the human injury and pain inflicted by errors such as slavery and civil war; notes her husband to be uncommonly fair and open-minded and she herself to be uncommonly fortunate and happy. #6249-a.
    - Jane M. Pierce to Nathaniel Hawthorne, 1863, ALS, 3 pp. on 2 l. (Box-folder 3:9a)
      Jane Pierce thanks Hawthorne for expressing his appreciation of Franklin Pierce as a life-long friend and a leader in the dedicatiaon and preface to Our old home. She notes that her husband is unwell and sends regards to Hawthorne's family. In a postscript she comments on what parts of the book she most enjoyed. Docket on verso reads "Mrs. Pierce to Hawthorne. Handed to me by Mrs. Hawthorne June 1864" indicating the return of the letter to Pierce as a souvenir of Jane after her death. #6249-j.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to General [Franklin Pierce], 1863 November 6, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:10)
      Expresses concern for General Pierce's health, reports on Julian's residence and schedule in Cambridge, and questions whether his recent letter might have included postage stamps by accident or for Hawthorne's use for their correspondence, given the discontinuation of Pierce's franking privilege by "our shabby legislators." #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1863 November 13, ALS, 7 pp. on 2 l. folded, with autograph envelope. (Box-folder 3:11)
      Like her husband, rejects retaliating against the South for its treatment of prisoners and argues against vengeful punishment of those held in the North's prisons, a policy that would defy God's law, demean the perpetrator, belie America's identity as "an ideal nation, fighting for justice, liberty, civilization, and Christian manners," and surely provoke worse southern vengeance. Believing the general to share these views, she reports that her sister Mrs. Mann and friend Mr. Emerson feel otherwise. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1863 November 22, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope. (Box-folder 3:12)
      Correcting her November 13 comment that Mr. Emerson favors retaliating against the South for vengeful prisoner treatment, as Mr. Hawthorne's subsequent discussion with their friend revealed otherwise. #6249-a.
    - Franklin Pierce to F.N. Bloor, 1863 November 23, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:13)
      Discusses real estate matters and closes with a recommendation of N. Hawthorne's recent book Our Old Home. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Madam," 1864 February 4, ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l., with the following: Goodspeed's Catalogue no. 25 (September 1904) listing and illustrating the letter; a copy on tracing-paper; a typed excerpt from a letter C.E.F. Clark, Jr., sent in 1963 to Barrett concerning the tracing-paper copy and catalogue; and a typed transcript, 1 p. (3 copies). (Box-folder 3:14)
      Regrets his belated response to her request for "my autograph, accompanied with a patriotic sentiment, for the benefit of the Sanitary Fair" and laments that, while full of feeling for his country's crisis, he finds no words for them. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Franklin] Pierce, 1864 March 9, ALS, 1 p., with a printed account of Nathaniel Hawthorne's final trip with Pierce, his death, subsequent events, related letters (pp. 345-352 from N.H.'s son Julian's biography of him). (Box-folder 3:15)
      Needs to get stronger before visiting Boston, but now "expect[s] to go on improving to a reasonable extent- which at one time, in my secret mind, I hardly hoped for." #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to "My dear friend" [General E.A. Hitchcock], 1864 March 16, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. folded, with an autograph envelope. (Box-folder 3:16)
      Thanks him for his letter of concern for her, noting what peace his words bring her, even when her mind is not equal to the demands of his philosophical writings; reports that she has found a dear friend with whom to share her thoughts and feelings during stressful times and with N.H. away; thinks travel to Europe likely to benefit her and her children as it would the hard-working general himself. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to Sidney Webster, 1864 March 14, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded, with a typed transcript, 1 p. (Box-folder 3:17)
      To fulfill Webster's request on his wife's behalf, sends one fragment of manuscript and notes that he usually burns work he has finished and is sorry to find nothing better for her album. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to [Franklin] Pierce, 1864 May 7, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with ALS, S[ophia] Hawthorne to General Pierce, [1864 May 8], 1 p. on the verso of N.H.'s letter, and also F. Pierce's annotation that the letter was the last written by N.H.; with photocopies of both letters and a handwritten transcript of N.H.'s letter (on Goodspeed's letterhead). (Box-folder 3:18)
      Despite persisting poor health, expects in a few days to begin their planned trip. Sophia notes with pleasure that N.H. is strong enough to write his note despite persistent ill-health and adds that she will accompany him to meet Pierce, then proceed alone to Boston. #6249-a.
    - E.A. Hitchcock to Miss [Elizabeth] Peabody, 1864 June 3, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:19)
      Expresses his sympathies on learning of N.H.'s death from her recent letter, asks that she convey them also to Mrs. Hawthorne, and rejoices that the latter has found strength to accept the loss. #6249-d.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to Howard Ticknor, 1864 June 24, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:20)
      Requests that he, in Mr. Fields's absence, remit funds by check. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1864 August 7, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:21)
      Praises General Hitchcock and, in effusive and symbolic language, describes how his books have given her peace and the sense of being one with her beloved husband, despite his death. Puzzles over the general's roles as religious teacher versus his war work in Washington, or, "why the Interpreter of the Prince of Peace should be Counselor of War. But I feel safer that you are.. ." #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1865 December 6, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope. (Box-folder 3:22)
      Acknowledges General Hitchcock's gift of one of his books, his works revealing of the "Holy of holies" for her and kept in her "mystic, magic library". #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to "My dear friend" [General E.A. Hitchcock], 1866 February 14, ALS, 11 pp. on 3 l. folded, with autograph envelope. (Box-folder 3:23)
      Thanking him for one of his books and pouring forth her Christian spiritual beliefs including the importance of his writings in spiritual matters. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to Lydia, 1866 October 1, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:24)
      Having received no letter from her cousin for some time, fears that Lydia is unwell and writes, though ill herself, to plead for some word. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to Lydia, 1866 October 4, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:25)
      Reports her safe return from a short visit with her cousin and other relatives. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to Lydia, 1866 October 14, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:26)
      Enquires about relatives and reports that her own children are away and she is alone. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to Augustine, 1866 October 27, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:27)
      Enquires about his return home to Amherst after visiting her and about other relatives; reports on problems getting the stove she ordered and on her own children, especially on Rose, who is beginning school in Lexington. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to "My dear friend" [General E.A. Hitchcock], 1866 December 30, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. folded, with autograph envelope also bearing his annotation. (Box-folder 3:28)
      Discusses her reading during an illness, including an Atlantic article on the authorship of Shakespeare's works, then Delia Bacon on the subject, then Sir Francis Bacon's writings, and then the general's analysis of the sonnets and other literary works. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to "My dear friend" [General E.A. Hitchcock], 1867 March 3, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope also bearing his annotation. (Box-folder 3:29)
      Explains how ill she has been, how welcome his letter was, and what reading it suggested to her to undertake. Reports her sister Elizabeth plans a deserved trip to Europe and Julian wishes to study in Heidelberg for several years, taking her and his sisters along; as she lives "only for her children" and thinks this a good plan she is considering how she might finance it if her recovery allows. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to "My dear little pet" [Cousin Lydia], 1867 May 12, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:30)
      Reports family news: Julian's slow progress on arranging to study in Europe and taking his mother and sisters along; Una's happiness about her recent engagement to Storrow Higginson, whom Sophia will welcome to the family; Rose's changing schools and her having a tutor in Europe; her sister Elizabeth's impending European journey; and the ill health of both her sister Mary her hard-working husband Horace Mann. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1867 August 4, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope also bearing his annotation. (Box-folder 3:31)
      Thanks him for sending the Preface and praises all his work; reports Mrs. Mann is very ill; expects that "a sudden failure of means" will prevent her and the children from going to Europe as they had hoped and that for now they will vacation at Rye beach. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, [1867 September], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope also bearing his annotation. (Box-folder 3:32)
      Is delighted with and benefiting from his book he sent her; reports feeling better in general, especially since Julian's plan to study in Europe was abandoned for want of means, a disappointment he took gracefully, substituting for it the study of civil engineering; is blessed to find such character in all her children. Is pleased that his tenure as commissioner general of prisons has ended. #6249-a.
    - S[ophia] Hawthorne to "My dear friend" [General E.A. Hitchcock], 1867 October 20, ALS, 8 pp. on 2 l. folded, with autograph envelope also bearing his annotation. (Box-folder 3:33)
      Expresses her deep concern about his recent serious illness, wishing never to be without him and his wisdom; comments on several of his books, especially his Bible commentary, so instructive to her. Reports how faithful, good, intelligent, and sensitive Julian is as son and brother, as the quote she excerpts from his recent letter shows. #6249-a.
    - Julian Hawthorne to Gen. [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1868 February 9, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded, with autograph envelope also bearing his annotation. (Box-folder 3:34)
      Writes for his ailing mother, who is worried about General Hitchcock's illness, and requests that he have a friend write her about his progress. #6249-a.
    - Franklin Pierce to Sarah Webster, 1868 March 18, ALS, 12 pp. on 3 l. folded, with typed transcript, 2 pp. (Box-folder 3:35)
      Sends her as promised the last letter Nathaniel Hawthorne wrote, addressed to himself before their then-impending trip together to New Hampshire; recalls painfully their long, close friendship, N.H.'s support during the final illness and death of Mrs. Pierce, and details of their long-planned journey: choosing the route and itinerary, N.H.'s refusing Pierce's suggestions for making their trip less taxing, N.H.'s terming it a "boon" to experience death without a struggle, and, at the Pemigewasset House in Plymouth, New Hampshire, during the early morning hours of 18 May 1864, finding him to be not asleep but lifeless. #6249-a.
    - Sophia Hawthorne to General [E.A.] Hitchcock, 1868 June 7, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:36)
      Feeling better, she congratulates him on his marriage, delights in the prospect of reading his further writings, and reveals that she is soon to sell her home, the Wayside. #6249-a.
    - G[eorge] P[arsons] Lathrop to "Brainerd," 1882 August 23, ALS, 8 pp. on 3 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:37)
      Discusses literary matters, primarily incidents and conflicts involving Julian Hawthorne and his father's unpublished manuscript fragments [especially, the story fragment Dr. Grimshawe's Secret, 1883], his inaccurate claims about them, copyright ownership, and publication efforts. #6249-a.
    - Elizabeth P. Peabody to "Charles," 1886 June 27, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:38)
      Sends a scrap [filed in the Hawthorne Papers with his manuscripts], a sentence she thinks N.H. clipped from one of his old manuscripts [i.e., Time's Portraiture, 1838], "that he had lain away as an autograph," offering it in response to her friend's request for one. #6249-a.
    - G[eorge] P[arsons] Lathrop to "My dear Sir," 1888 June 5, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:39)
      Responds to an enquiry about the basis for N.H.'s story The Minister's Black Veil, saying that there was no "original" for what was purely the author's own creation, as was the case with The House of the Seven Gables. #6249-a.
    - A[lexander] Ireland to M[oncure] D. Conway, 1890 April 6, ALS, 7 pp. on 2 l. folded, including his autograph transcript (1 p.) of Nathaniel Hawthorne's ALS (28 November 1853) to Ireland; with typed transcript from a dealer's catalogue entry describing the letter. (Box-folder 3:40)
      Recounts meeting Nathaniel Hawthorne and touring an exhibition with him during which Alfred Tennyson entered the same gallery but, much to Ireland's dismay, the two did not meet, as N.H., thinking it would be improper to speak when they had never been formally and properly introduced, firmly declined Ireland's pleas to seize the opportunity (but notes that the description of Tennyson in English Notebooks shows in what detail Hawthorne observed him in those few moments). Also, Ireland supplied a holograph copy of N.H.'s 1853 letter to him declining an invitation to a dinner in honor of poet Charles Swain. #6249-d.
  - Subseries B: Undated and Partially Dated Letters
    - S[ophia] A. Hawthorne to R.W. Griswold, n.y. September 23, ANS, 1 p. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:41)
      Declining an invitation on behalf of her husband. #6249-a.
    - Una Hawthorne to Mr. [Alexander?] Strahan, n.y. September 29, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:42)
      A self-deprecating letter requesting advice about poems she had written and where to submit them for publication (Sunday Magazine likely, in her own view), her only motive being that of earning money "to help in the Home where I am working." Any further compositions of hers would be in prose with her name never to appear on them. #6249-a.
    - N[athaniel] H[awthorne] to E[lizabeth Peabody], n.d., ALS, 1 p. on 1 clipped fragment, bearing on the recto a portion of a Sophia Hawthorne letter; with a typed transcript of both (1 p.). (Box-folder 3:43)
      Encourages her "coming over" to be with her sister Sophia, noted briefly on the verso of a leaf bearing 10 lines of a letter in his wife's hand, in which she discusses matters relating to children and mentions an incident at the consulate. #6249-a.
    - Nath[anie]l Hawthorne to "Dear Sir," n.d., ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:44)
      Deferring execution of an unidentified plan. #6249-a.
    - Una [Hawthorne] to Miss Kortright, Monday, n.y., ALS, 4 pp., the first black-bordered, on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:45)
      Declines an invitation for them to live with her [probably at the time of her mother Sophia Hawthorne's death in London, 26 February 1871] as she and her sister Rose plan to maintain themselves in the house where they lived with their mother; will send some of her mother's hair, as requested, and soon prepare the room where her mother lies for friends' visitation the next day. #6249-f.
- Series III: Miscellaneous Manuscripts
  - Legal scrap signed by Edward Rawson, secret[ary], for John Hawthorne and others, plaintiffs, against Henry Webb, defendant, Essex [County, Massachusetts], 1659 May 25, MDS, 1 p. on 1 l., with typed partial transcript from a dealer's catalogue. (Box-folder 3:46)
  - Survey for William Hawthorne by Jonathan Danforth, signed by Edwd. Rawson, 1675 June 18, MDS, 2 pp. on 1 l. folded. (Box-folder 3:47)
    Includes a manuscript map of the 640 acre square, designated "Maj: Hawthorne, his farme at Mistequassuck." #6249-a.
  - Warrant pursuant to the complaint of Mary Harris against Nathaniel Clark, signed by John Hawthorne, Justice of the Peace, 1707/8 February 3, MDS, 2 pp. on 1 l. (Box-folder 3:48)